Guide to the Victorian Society of America, Metropolitan Chapter Records 1950s-2019 (bulk 1970-2015) MS 3205
New-York Historical Society
Victorian Society of America, Metropolitan Chapter records
1950s-2019 (bulk 1970-2015)
New-York Historical Society
Victorian Society in America. Metropolitan Chapter
MS 3205
12 Linear feet in 12 record cartons
7.69 Gigabytes (7,887 files)
Since 1966, the Victorian Society in America (VSA) has been committed to protecting, promoting, and preserving Victorian-era (1837-1901) and Edwardian-era (1901-circa 1914) arts, architecture, and culture in the United States. The collection includes print and digital administrative records, correspondence, publications, and ephemera of the founding and early years of the Victorian Society in America (circa 1966-1970) and of the Metropolitan Chapter of the VSA (1970-2018).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Paper-based Files, 1950s-2019 (bulk 1970-2015)
Series II: Digital Files, circa 1966-circa 2014
Biographical / Historical
The Victorian Society in America (VSA) is a membership society that, since 1966, has been committed to protecting, promoting, and preserving Victorian-era (1837-1901) and Edwardian-era (1901-circa 1914) arts, architecture, and culture in the United States. The VSA is a sister society of the Victorian Society in the U.K. and often collaborates on educational programming, most notably its Summer Schools, in conjunction with the U.K. organization. The VSA is headquartered in Philadelphia, PA, and is a registered nonprofit.
The VSA was founded in New York City by noted preservationists Margot Gayle, Brendan Gill, and Henry-Russell Hitchcock (who was also a founding member of the U.K. society), among others, and who were inspired to act by the demolition of New York's Pennsylvania Station [McKim, Mead, and White, extant 1910-1963]. Soon after its founding, the VSA based its headquarters in Philadelphia, PA.
In January 1970, sixty-nine members in the New York City metropolitan area petitioned the VSA for permission to organize a New York Chapter. Among the signers were professors and architectural historians: Marvin Schwartz, Adolph Placzek, George Collins, James Marston Fitch; writers: Louis Auchincloss, Clay Lancaster, Ada Louise Huxtable; architects: Giorgio Cavaglieri, Philip Johnson; and preservation activists: Mr. and Mrs. Everett Ortner and Margot Gayle. In March 1970, the Metropolitan Chapter (VSNY) began operating as a registered nonprofit Chapter of the VSA.
In the early years of the Chapter, membership and dues were paid to the VSA national organization with a portion returned to the Chapters for programming and operations. Formalization of the Chapter structure in the mid-1970s and the development and adoption of VSA Chapter-specific bylaws eventually allowed Chapters to directly receive membership dues. Members also eventually were allowed the option to join just the Chapter or Chapter and the national society—independent of each other—and Chapters could solicit funds for specific projects. (Currently, only VSNY Board Members are required to be a member of both organizations.) This change in funding structure appears to have energized the development of VSNY's membership, programming, and preservation advocacy and projects.
In 1976, the VSNY Board began recognizing excellence in publications, exhibitions, preservation advocacy, restoration, individual achievement, lifetime achievement and other categories by bestowing awards during its Annual Meeting (May). The number of award categories and awardees has grown significantly over the years. Around 1987/1988, the VSNY began awarding scholarships for individuals to attend the VSA Summer Schools in Newport, Rhode Island and, later, the Victorian Society (U.K.) Summer Schools in the United Kingdom and other destinations. The VSNY also produces public history programming, including the Hands on History series for students.
In 1983, the VSNY began publishing a semi-annual newsletter. Before founding its own newsletter, the VSNY communicated to members through the VSA's national publication, The Victorian, which is well-represented in the first half of this chronologically arranged archive.
Also in 1983, the VSNY was host to the VSA's national conference and Annual Meeting, and the Chapter organized events, tours, and social gatherings through New York City in addition to hosting the conference sessions.
The VSA was founded in preservation advocacy—and it continues to be active in preservation efforts across New York City and State. Past major education and preservation campaigns included the SoHo-Cast Iron Historic District (designated 1973) and the expansion of the SoHo Historic District (circa 2006, designated 2010); Pier A (designated 1977), the last surviving municipal pier; the New York County (Tweed) Courthouse 1861-1872 (designated 1984), the second oldest surviving city government building, and Tin Pan Alley (designated 2019), comprised of five adjoining buildings along West 28th Street in Manhattan and the birthplace of American popular music.
The Chapter was also instrumental in funding a major restoration of the Sherman Monument—a gilded-bronze equestrian statue of Sherman by Augustus Saint-Gaudens which sits atop a base designed by Charles McKim—located in Grand Army Plaza at 5th Avenue and 59th Street. In 1985/1986, the Society began a campaign to raise awareness and funds for its stabilization, preservation, and restoration and held a symposium on "The Heroic Age of American Sculpture."
VSNY members, advisors, and Board members regularly present testimony at New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission (LPC) hearings in support of historic site designation and protection. Circa 2015, the VSA undertook a campaign to testify for sites threatened with de-calendaring due to LPC application backlog. Members of the board also routinely attend and speak at the City Planning Commission and the City Council on issues important to VSNY's purpose.
In 2003, the Margot Gayle Fund, which underwrites grants for historic preservation, was approved at the VSNY Annual Meeting. The first award funded professional research into the cast iron buildings of Manhattan's SoHo district. This research was the basis of the VSNY's 2006 report that was used to argue for the extension of the SoHo-Cast Iron Historic District. Activities included the publication of the report, testimony and letters of support, media outreach, community engagement, guided walking tours of the historic district, and publication of a new edition of "Cast Iron Architecture in New York City" by Margot Gayle and Edmund V. Gillion, Jr. [Friends of Cast Iron Architecture (FCIA), 1974, 1983; VSA Metropolitan Chapter on behalf of (FCIA), 2011].
VSNY produces a regularly scheduled slate of educational lectures and seminars on architecture, decorative arts, fine arts, landscape, literature, and cultural history pertaining to the Victorian and Edwardian eras. The society also organizes tours of special exhibitions; offers guided neighborhood walks; and arranges for visits to historical sites, gardens, and private homes. Tours cover sites in greater New York City area as well as nearby regions including the Hudson River Valley and Long Island, New York; Fairfield County, Connecticut; the Berkshire region in Massachusetts; Cape May, New Jersey; and other destinations.
The VSNY also sponsors events in collaboration with other organizations such as the Society of Architectural Historians, Friends of Cast Iron Architecture, Historic Districts Council, and Classical America, among other organizations.
The Society has published some compiled lists of Board members and events and tours found in this collection as well as more recent VSNY newsletters on its website, https://vicsocny.org.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Metropolitan Chapter of the Victorian Society in America, Inc., May 2019.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the records of the Metropolitan (i.e., New York City-based) Chapter of the Victorian Society of America. These records include Board and Annual meeting minutes, treasurer's/financial reports, membership materials, event and other publicity, presentations, photographs, and more. The bulk of the records range from the 1970s to 2015 and so include both paper-based and digital formats.
Architecture -- United States -- 19th century.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century.; Cast-iron fronts (Architecture) -- New York (State) -- New York (N.Y.).; Decoration and ornament -- Edwardian style; Decoration and ornament -- Victorian style.; Decoration and ornament, Architectural -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration.; Historic districts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic preservation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Monuments -- New York (State) -- New York.; Societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); SoHo (New York, N.Y.); Administrative records.; Clippings (information artifacts); Film negatives; Financial records.; Fliers (printed matter); Letters (correspondence); Membership lists.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Photographs.; Promotional materials.; Research (documents); Testimonies.; Victorian Society in America; Victorian Society in America. Metropolitan Chapter -- Archives.; Dane, William J., 1923-2019; Gayle, Margot
- Series I. Paper-based Files, 1950s-2019 (bulk 1970-2015); 12 Linear feet in 12 record cartons
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes the paper-based records of the Victorian Society of America, Metropolitan Chapter (VSNY), with some early records of the parent organization. Overall, the VSNY records include newsletters, Board minutes and other governance matters, financial records, event publicity, membership forms, and other material ranging from the 1970s to 2019.
  The files retain VSNY's original chronological order and the coding structure used by VSNY to arrange each year's documents by subject matter. These codes (i.e, letters A to X) were used consistently to sequence the folders for newsletters, minutes, and so forth for each year. Following is a description of the content for the letter codes used by VSNY for the records. However, not all documents/codes are present in every year.
  Folder Code A) Metropolitan Chapter Newsletters
  VSNY began publishing a Chapter newsletter in 1983. The newsletter is published twice a year, in the spring and fall, with occasional additional issues and/or a Chapter update leaflets. The newsletter contains news and updates on VSNY's preservation advocacy; VSNY awards, scholarships, and grants; VSA Summer Schools; Board news and interviews, member news and lists; past events; and comprehensive calendar of all lectures, seminars, and tours; among other recurring features.
  Folders contain as many extant copies as were delivered by VSNY and some issues are missing.
  Before 1983 news from the VSA Chapters was contained within the VSA's national publication, The Victorian; see Folder Code J) National Publications.
  See also:
  – Series II, Digital, may contain draft articles and photos submitted to the newsletter and some PDFs of printed issues
  – Issues from 2007-present are available at https://vicsocny.org
  Folder Code B) Board Minutes
  Contains extant monthly Board meeting agendas, minutes and, possibly, some correspondence outside of Board meetings that affect agenda items.
  The VSNY Board begins its term on July 1, annually, and ends on June 30. From July to September VSNY Committees meet to plan the next year and the monthly board meetings begin in September. In earlier years, Board terms of service were limited to one year and, eventually, VSNY adopted longer, multi-year terms.
  Of note, some VSNY Board Members, such as William (Bill) J. Dane, served on VSA national's board and committees, and VSNY correspondence may sometimes be commingled with national business (Folder Code K).
  – Folder Code C) Treasurer's Reports
  – Folder Code D) Annual Meeting
  – Folder Code I) Officers and Volunteers, for committee lists, resignations and absences, and board nominations
  – Folder Code K) VSA National Conference and Tours / National Board Minutes
  – Series II, Digital: Contains some agendas and minutes in digital format (e.g., Microsoft Word DOC).
  Folder Code C) Treasurer's Reports and Budgets
  Contains annual budgets and projections, year-to-date accounting distributed at Board meetings and the Annual Meeting, paid invoices, and sometimes cancelled checks, ledgers, and receipts for petty cash.
  Folder Code D) Annual Meeting
  Contains flyers, postcards, and/or invitations to the VSNY Annual Meeting, held annually in May, at a historic location in New York City. The Annual Meeting is a public Board meeting and a continuation of business from Folder Code B) Board Minutes. Nominees to the VSNY Board and some administrative issues are voted on by members at the Annual Meeting. Occasionally may also contain duplicates of VSNY Award documents, speakers' scripts, and/or 35mm presentation slides. May also contain minor ephemera such as venue information, history, and correspondence about the venue.
  – Series II, Digital: May contain photos from Annual Meetings, PowerPoint files, and miscellaneous Annual Meeting-related correspondence.
  Folder Code E) Lectures
  Contains flyers, postcards and/or invitations to VSNY-hosted lectures. May also contain administrative records as to brainstorming and planning, speaker biographies, and attendee lists. (Does not include scripts, slides, or materials from the presentation.) Note that in some programming years, the VSNY employed a Publicity Committee to send press releases to local newspapers and other media outlets to promote upcoming events. If an announcement was formatted as a press release, it may be located in Folder Code V) Media Contacts / Press Releases.
  Folder Code F) Tours
  Contains flyers, postcards and/or invitations to VSNY-hosted tours. May also contain administrative records as to brainstorming and planning, budgets and bills, correspondence, attendee lists, research materials, and, occasionally, tour guide scripts. Note that in some programming years, the VSNY employed a Publicity Committee to send press releases to local newspapers and other media outlets to promote upcoming events. If an announcement was formatted as a press release, it may be located in Folder Code V) Media Contacts / Press Releases.
  Folder Code G) Preservation Advocacy
  Contains correspondence with government agencies, planning authorities, NYC Landmarks Preservation Commission, and others, voicing VSNY support for restoration projects and landmark designation and identify sites and structures falling into disrepair. As preservation advocacy touches most, if not all, parts of VSNY's operations, materials may be found across numerous folders.
  Folder Code H) Special Events / Parties / Fundraisers
  Contains invitations and occasional photographs from events outside of the regular calendar of Lectures, Tours, Annual Meeting, and Summer Schools. Often, there were two to three special events per year, including a summer social outing, winter VSA Summer School scholarship fundraiser, and a holiday- or new year-themed tour or event.
  Folder Code I) Officers and Volunteers
  Contains lists of Board members and Officers; Committee assignments; descriptions of roles and responsibilities; Nominating Committee candidates, candidate resumes, and memos; and contact information. May also contain communications about Board business not discussed within the context of a Board or Annual Meeting, such as notes of absence, letters of acceptance and resignation, Board packets, and other Board management materials.
  – Folder Code B) Board Minutes
  – Folder Code C) Annual Meeting
  Folder Code J) VSA [National] Publications
  Contains printed newsletters produced by the national VSA organization. Note that before 1983, the VSNY did not produce a Chapter newsletter, so the bulk of inclusive dates are from the mid-1980s and earlier.
  Folder Code K) VSA National Conference and Tours / National Board Minutes
  Contains invitations, schedules and agendas, attendee packets, and information and administrative correspondence about the VSA Annual Meeting. Also contains VSA national Board Agendas and Minutes.
  Folder Code L) Summer School
  The VSA Summer School program is managed by the VSA (U.S.) national organization and the Victorian Society (U.K.) sister organization. VSA Summer Schools are held in the United Kingdom and other European destinations; Newport, Rhode Island; and Chicago, Illinois, and alumni of the program are enrolled in a non-regional VSA Alumni Association Chapter. Contents may include brochures and info session materials, applications and related correspondence, enrollment lists, photos, thank you notes from attendees, and other related materials. The VSNY and VSA offer scholarships to defray the costs of the program so VSA Summer School scholarship correspondence may also be filed in Folder Code N) Awards and Scholarships.
  Folder Code M) Education
  Primarily includes local VSNY programs such as Hands On History student engagement programs.
  – Folder Code E) Lectures
  – Folder Code F) Tours
  – Folder Code L) VSA Summer School
  Folder Code N) Awards and Scholarships
  Contents include nominations, applications, and information for a VSNY Award, which began in 1976. Submission categories include, but are not limited to, recognizing excellence in publications, preservation advocacy, restoration, individual achievement, exhibition, lifetime achievement and other categories by bestowing awards during its Annual Meeting (May). The number of award categories and awardees has grown significantly over the years. Scholarship applications and correspondence concerning the VSA Summer Schools may be contained in Folder Code L) Summer School.
  Folder Code O) Membership
  Contains membership forms, flyers, and brochures; membership lists and/or labels; and some correspondence.
  Folder Code P) Legal / Operations / Bylaws
  Contains VSNY operational documents such as liability insurance contracts, space use and rental contracts, tax exemption certificates, and bylaws and bylaw updates.
  Folder Code Q) Correspondence
  Contains general correspondence between VSNY and members and related organizations. May also contain acknowledgement of donations to and by the VSNY.
  – Folder Code D) Treasurer's Reports and Budgets
  Folder Code R) VSA Correspondence with Chapters
  Contents include correspondence between the VSNY and the VSA national organization regarding the filing of annual reports with the national organization (bulk) as well as some minor correspondence between chapters.
  Folder Code S) Special Publications
  This Folder Code is rarely used as most VSNY special publications overlap with cast iron preservation.
  Folder T) Margot Gayle Papers / Fund / Projects
  Contents include personal papers and ephemera collected by Margot Gayle. Contents mostly concern VSNY business but also includes some projects, advocacy, photos, and work with the Friends of Cast Iron Architecture, of which she was a founding member. In 2003, the Margot Gayle Fund was established to fund preservation awards. After Gayle's death in 2008, applications for the Margot Gayle Fund and correspondence on funded Projects make up the bulk of this Folder Code.
  Please note that Margot Gayle served simultaneously on VSNY's Board as well as the Friends of Cast Iron Architecture (FCIA) and some materials produced by FCIA are included in Gayle's VSNY papers.
  – Folder Code G) Preservation Advocacy
  – Folder Code X) Cast Iron Advocacy
  Folder Code U) Stationery
  Contains extant samples of VSNY letterhead and/or envelopes. Early letterhead lists Board members and Officers and are offset printed. Later letterhead is digitally printed and without Board and Officer lists.
  Folder V) Media Contacts / Press Releases
  Contains NYC metropolitan area media contacts. Also includes VSNY lecture and tour announcements formatted as press releases generated by the VSNY Publicity Committee.
  – Series I, Papers, E) Lectures
  – Series I, Papers, F) Tours
  – Series I, Papers, H) Special Events / Parties / Fundraisers
  Folder Code W) Name Change
  Contents include correspondence among VSNY Board members and between VSNY and the VSA national organization regarding changing the Chapter's name to better reflect New York City and the commissioning of a new logo. The correspondence concludes in 2011 with VSA national rejecting the proposed name change but approving new artwork.
  Folder Code X) Cast Iron Advocacy
  Contents include materials related to the research (correspondence, maps, site photos, contracts, etc.) of cast iron buildings in SoHo in preparation for a petition to designate (NYC LPC designated, 1973) and later extend (NYC LPC designated, 2010) the SoHo Cast Iron Historic District. Contents also include promotional materials and artifacts, newspaper clippings, inventories and commissioned surveys, photographs, and correspondence with the NYC Landmarks Preservation Commission (LPC) concerning the applications. Also includes materials for walking tours and printed editions of Cast Iron Architecture in New York City by Margot Gayle and Edmund V. Gillion, Jr. [Friends of Cast Iron Architecture (FCIA), ©1974, 1983; VSA Metropolitan Chapter on behalf of FCIA, ©2011].
  Arrangement
  The series opens with documents about the organization's history, then moves into sets of folders arranged chronologically. As noted in the Scope Note, each set, with one or two years of documents, is further arranged by subject content. This chronological and subject arrangement follows the original order of VSNY's archive.
  Some materials circa 2000-circa 2015 may be available in Series II, Digital Files. For example, Board Meeting minutes for December 5, 2005 (.DOC), are available in Series II-Digital Files, but may not have been printed for the paper-based files.
  - History—Legal and Founding Documents, 1966-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Among other items, includes copies of incorporation papers, tax certificates, as well as rubber stamps used for check deposits and other administration.
  - History—VSA Stationery and Membership Materials, circa 1980s-circa 1990s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Among other items, includes various printed ephemera (book plates, membership cards, letterhead, envelopes, membership brochures, etc.) bearing the VSA national logo and Philadelphia address (bulk) and undated VSNY ephemera.
  - History—Organizational Histories (various dates) and Margot Gayle Interviews (2001) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Organizational histories are undated. Among other items, includes printed transcript of interview(s) with Margot Gayle (2001).
  - History—William (Bill) J. Dane on VSA and VSNY and Preservation, 2002, 2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Among other items, includes transcripts of oral history interviews (2010) and administrative forms. Most transcripts are drafts without final corrections. See also Series II, Digital for original audio recordings and final, approved transcripts in .DOC format.
  - History—Augustus Saint-Gaudens' Sherman Monument Restoration, circa 1986, circa 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Among other items, includes documents dating from the 1986 project and transcripts of oral history interviews with Billie Britz (1996?) and Margot Gayle (1996?) about the VSNY project.
  - History—Compiled List of Board Members, 1967-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)